A Guide to the William Blathwayt Papers, 1631-1722
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
William Blathwayt Papers 1680-1700
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 1946.2
2564 items.
Blathwayt, William
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1946
Biographical Information
British colonial official, Secretary of the Lords of Trade and Plantations (1679-1710).
Scope and Content
Papers consist chiefly of letters written to Blathwayt by colonial governors and others. Includes some drafts of letters by Blathwayt. Subjects include French and Indian troubles, military defense, illegal trade, the Navigation Acts, charter of Massachusetts, piracy in the Caribbean, Virginia tobacco trade, wars in Jamaica, the slave question in the Leeward Islands, troubles between governors and the assembly in Bermuda. Included is a copy of "The Declaration of the People Against Sir Wm. Berkeley..." (1676) by Nathaniel Bacon, Jr.; and an original draft of the Charter of Pennsylvania (1681).
Arrangement
The items are arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Persons:
Bacon, Nathaniel, ca. 1620-1692; Baltimore, Charles Calvert, Baron, 1699-1751; Bacon, Nathaniel, 1648-1676; Beeston, William, Sir, b. 1636; Bellomont, Richard Coote, Earl of, 1636-1701; Byrd, William, 1652-1704; Byrd, William, 1674-1744; Chicheley, Henry, Sir, 1615-1683; Codrington, Christopher, 1640-1698; Watson, Francis, Sir; Howard of Effingham, Francis Howard, Baron, 1643-1695; Dudley, Joseph, 1647-1720; Fletcher, Benjamin, 1640-1703; Culpeper, Thomas, Sir, 1626-1697; Ludwell, Philip, 1672-1727; Lynch, Thomas, Sir, d. 1684; Mather, Increase, 1639-1723; Pepys, Samuel, 1633-1703; Morgan, Henry, Sir, 1635?-1688; Nicholson, Francis, 1655-1728; Penn, William, 1644-1718; Phips, William, Sir, 1651-1695; Randolph, Edward, ca. 1632-1703; Spencer, Nicholas, d. 1689; Spotswood, Alexander, 1676-1740; Stoughton, William, 1632-1701; Van Cortlandt, Stephanus, 1643-1700; Brattle, William, 1662-1717; Codrington, Christopher, 1668-1710; Limerick, Thomas Dongan, Earl of, 1634-1715; Hinckley, Thomas, ca. 1618-1706; Molesworth, Hender; Cony, Richard; Copley, Lionel, 1648-1693; Cranfield, Edward; Cranston, Abraham; Plater, George; Ritchier, Isaac; Robinson, Robert; Stapleton, William, Sir; Wharton, Richard; Beverley, Robert, ca. 1673-1722; Banister, John, 1650-1692; Blair, James, 1656-1743; Digges, Dudley, 1655-1710; Jenings, Edmund, 1659-1727; Leisler, Jacob, d. 1691; Page, John, d. 1710; Wormeley, Ralph, 1650-1701; Blathwayt, William, 1649?-1717
Subjects:
Slavery, Leeward Islands (West Indies), History, 17th century; Bacon's Rebellion, 1676
Geographical Names:
United States, Politics and government, To 1775; Bermuda Island (Bermuda Islands), History, 17th century; United States, History, Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Jamaica, History, To 1962; Bermuda Island (Bermuda Islands), Politics and government, 17th century; Jamaica, Politics and government; Pennsylvania, History, Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775
Collection Contents
- Volume I
  - Number 1: Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island, Connecticut, 1682 October -1683 August (10 pieces) (Box Box 1)
  - Number 2: Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island, 1683 September -1685/6 January (12 pieces)
  - Number 3: New England, New York, 1686 May -1686 July (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: New England, New York, 1686 July -1687 August (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: Massachusetts, New Hampshire, New York, 1687 August -1688 October (15 pieces)
  - Number 6: New York, Massachusetts, Connecticut, 1688 October -1689 July (8 pieces)
  - Number 7: Massachusetts, New Hampshire, New York, Connecticut, 1689 October 8-1689/90 January 10 (10 pieces)
- Volume II
  - Number 1: New York, Virginia, Ireland, 1683-1692 (5 pieces)
  - Number 2: Maryland, Virginia, 1692 May -1692 July (10 pieces)
  - Number 3: New York, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Pennsylvania, Virginia, 1692 August -1692/3 March(11 pieces)
  - Number 4: Maryland, New York, Massachusetts, Virginia, Pennsylvania, 1693 July -1698 July (13 pieces)
  - Number 5: Pennsylvania, New York, 1698 July -1698 September (10 pieces)
  - Number 6: Carolina, Bermuda, 1699-1700 (11 pieces)
- Volume III
  - Number 1: New England, New York, New Jersey, 1669-1680 (9 pieces)
  - Number 2: New England, 1686-1687 May (8 pieces)
  - Number 3: New England, New York New Jersey, 1687 July -1688 August (8 pieces)
  - Number 4: New England, New York, 1688 October -1689 June (13 pieces)
  - Number 5: New York, Virginia, Maryland, 1691 September -1693 (10 pieces)
  - Number 6: New York, New England, Virginia, Maryland, 1693/4 January 5-1695 June (10 pieces)
  - Number 7: New York, New England, Virginia, Maryland, 1695 June 6-1698 April (11 pieces)
- Volume IV
  - Number 1: Connecticut, Massachusetts, 1680 September -1691 May (12 pieces)
  - Number 2: Connecticut, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, 1681 October -1686 August (6 pieces)
  - Number 3: Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, New York, New Jersey, West Indies, Maryland, 1682/3 March-1685/6 December (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Massachusetts, 1691 April -1686 May (16 pieces)
  - Number 5: Connecticut, Massachusetts, 1685 April -1702 May (14 pieces)
- Volume V
  - Number 1: Massachusetts, 1692 May -1692/3 February(13 pieces) (Box Box 3)
  - Number 2: Massachusetts, 1693 April 6-1693/4 January 18 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Massachusetts, 1692-1693 (15 pieces)
  - Number 4: Massachusetts, Bermuda, July 1686-1689 (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: Massachusetts, October 1689-July 1695 (8 pieces)
  - Number 6: Massachusetts, November 1784-September 1696 (7 pieces)
- Volume VI
  - Number 1: New England, New York, July 1694-30 January 1696/7 (11 pieces)
  - Number 2: New England, New York, Pennsylvania, 16 January 1697/8-September 1702 (12 pieces)
  - Number 3: New England, New York, June 1680-August 1683 (11 pieces)
  - Number 4: New England, New York, December 1683-October 1686 (9 pieces)
  - Number 5: New England, February1677-October 1680 [1695] (12 pieces)
  - Number 6: New Plymouth, 1680-1691 (15 pieces)
- Volume VII
  - Number 1: Pennsylvania, New Jersey, March1680-1681 (1 piece) (Box Box 4)
  - Number 2: Pennsylvania, New Jersey, October 1682-1698 (4 pieces)
  - Number 3: Pennsylvania, New Jersey-Pirates, 1697-8, March-July 1699 (8 pieces)
  - Number 4: Pennsylvania, New Jersey, 1684-1702 (6 pieces)
- Volume VIII
  - Number 1: New York, December 1689-December 1701 (6 pieces)
  - Number 2: New York, August 1689-May 1691 (8 pieces)
  - Number 3: New York, September 1692-August 1693 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: New York, 1693-1694/5 (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: New York, May 1695-July 1698 (13 pieces)
  - Number 6: New York, November 1698-October 1700 (10 pieces)
  - Number 7: New York, 1699-1700 (7 pieces)
  - Number 8: New York, March1686-1687 (12 pieces)
- Volume IX
  - Number 1: New York, 1687-May 7, 1691 (11 pieces) (Box Box 5)
  - Number 2: New York, January 7, 1691-October 1693 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: New York, April 1694-May 1698 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: New York, July 1698-December 1699 (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: New York, December 1699-January 1701/2 (12 pieces)
  - Number 6: New York, 1700-1701 (6 pieces)
- Volume X
  - Number 1: New York, February1706-1710 (10 pieces)
  - Number 2: New York, December 1700-May 1701 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: New York, 1682/3-1696 (7 pieces)
  - Number 4: New York, September 1686-1687 (6 pieces)
  - Number 5: New York, New York, 1687-1691 (8 pieces)
  - Number 6: New York, 1692-1694 (10 pieces)
  - Number 7: New York, May 1695-October 1700 (13 pieces)
  - Number 8: New York, 1696-1700 (8 pieces)
- Volume XI
  - Number 1: New York, March1682/3-April 1714 (14 pieces) (Box Box 6)
  - Number 2: New York, May 1691-March1694 (7 pieces)
  - Number 3: New York, November 1694-March1698/9 (8 pieces)
  - Number 4: Rhode Island, August 1679-1696 (11 pieces)
- Volume XII
  - Number 1: New Hampshire, Massachusetts, June 1675-December 1684 (13 pieces)
  - Number 2: New Hampshire, Massachusetts, January 1684/5-September 1687 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: New Hampshire, Massachusetts, September 1696-January 1698/9 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: New Hampshire, Massachusetts, November 1695-October 1701 (9 pieces)
  - Number 5: Barbados, 1687-October 16881691 (7 pieces)
  - Number 6: Barbados, 1695-1697 (13 pieces)
- Volume XIII
  - Number 1: Virginia, 1676-July 1683 (13 pieces) (Box Box 7)
  - Number 2: Virginia, September 1683-March1689/90 (7 pieces)
  - Number 3: Virginia, May 1692-July 1693 (6 pieces)
  - Number 4: Virginia, December 1687-November 1692 (9 pieces)
  - Number 5, Virginia, February1692/3-April 29, 1697 (12 pieces)
  - Number 6: Virginia, June 1697-March1699 (6 pieces)
  - Number 7: Virginia, June 1700-1713 (8 pieces)
  - Number 8: Virginia, January 1705/6-October 1710 (5 pieces)
  - Number 9: Virginia, [1675]-[1715] (4 pieces)
- Volume XIV
  - Number 1: Virginia, November 1683-May 1684 (11 pieces)
  - Number 2: Virginia, New York, June 1684-December 9, 1684 (11 pieces)
  - Number 3: Virginia, February12, 1684/5-June 6 1685 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Virginia, June 21, 1685-May 10, 1686 (8 pieces)
  - Number 5: Virginia, August 1686-June 3, 1687 (10 pieces)
  - Number 6: Virginia, June 28, 1687-October 1689 (14 pieces)
  - Number 7: Virginia, July 1686-August 1688 (5 pieces)
- Volume XV
  - Number 1: New England, New York, Virginia, 1686/7-1691 (9 pieces) (Box Box 8)
  - Number 2: Virginia, New York, 7 May 1691-February1693 (10 pieces)
  - Number 3: Maryland, 1694-1698 (13 pieces)
  - Number 4: Virginia, 1698/9-1702 (7 pieces)
  - Number 5: Virginia, 1693-1697 (12 pieces)
  - Number 6: Virginia, June 1696-June 1713 (5 pieces)
  - Number 7: Virginia, May 1711-September 1715 (11 pieces)
- Volume XVI
  - Number 1: Virginia, May 1681-December 1682 (13 pieces)
  - Number 2: Virginia, February1682/3-November 1683 (10 pieces)
  - Number 3: Virginia, February1683/4-May 1685 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Virginia, June 1685-October 1687 (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: Virginia, October 1687-April 1688 (10 pieces)
- Volume XVII
  - Number 1: Virginia, [1679]-1680 (5 pieces) (Box Box 9)
  - Number 2: Virginia, 1680 (6 pieces)
  - Number 3: Virginia, October 1682-May 1683 (8 pieces)
  - Number 4: Virginia, 1680-1682 (4 pieces)
  - Number 5: Virginia, October 1689-January 1690 (7 pieces)
  - Number 6: Virginia, June 1691-February1692/3 (7 pieces)
  - Number 7: Virginia, July 1692-April 1715 (6 pieces)
  - Number 8: Virginia, 1689/90 (3 pieces)
  - Number 9: Virginia, 1657-1676 (6 pieces)
- Volume XVIII
  - Number 1: Maryland, 1678-1680 (7 pieces) (Box Box 10)
  - Number 2: Maryland, 1680/1-1683/4 and not dated (6 pieces)
  - Number 3: Maryland, Virginia, 1684-1699 (8 pieces)
  - Number 4: Maryland, 1692-1694 (7 pieces)
  - Number 5: Maryland, 1696-1697 (4 pieces)
  - Number 6: Maryland, 1692/3-1694 (8 pieces)
  - Number 7: Maryland, 1694-1695/6 (6 pieces)
  - Number 8: Maryland, 1696-1698 (7 pieces)
  - Number 9: Carolina, 1680-1698 and not dated (6 pieces)
- Volume XIX
  - Number 1: Newfoundland, New France, 1674-1691 and not dated (6 pieces)
  - Number 2: Newfoundland, 1695-1702 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Newfoundland, 16991620-1680 (5 pieces)
  - Fragments: Newfoundland
- Volume XX
  - Number 1: Plantation’s Office Accounts, 1680 September -December (13 pieces) (Box Box 11)
  - Number 2: Plantation Office Accounts, December 1683-March1684 (15 pieces)
  - Number 3: Plantation’s Office Accounts, March1683/4-June 1684 (12 pieces)
  - Number 4: Plantation Office Accounts, July -December 1684 (19 pieces)
  - Number 5: Plantation’s Office Accounts, January -June 1684/5 (20 pieces)
  - Number 6: Plantation’s Office Accounts, July -October 1685 (17 pieces)
  - Number 7: Plantation Office Accounts, November 1685-February1685/6 (14 pieces)
  - Number 8: Plantation’s Office Accounts, April 1686-April 1687 (22 pieces)
  - Number 9: Plantation’s Office Accounts: September 1692-June 1693 (12 pieces)
  - Number 10: Plantation Office Accounts, July 1693-March25, 1694 (13 pieces)
  - Number 11: Plantation’s Office Accounts, March28, 1694-March8, 1694/5 (15 pieces)
  - Number 12: Plantation’s Office Accounts: March23, 1695-December 24, 1695 (17 pieces)
  - Number 13: Plantation’s Office Accounts, December 25, 1695-October 1696 (13 pieces)
  - Number 14: Plantation’s Office Accounts, June 1697-October 1699 (12 pieces)
- Volume XXI
  - Number 1: Jamaica, September 1687-February1698/9 (8 pieces) (Box Box 12)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, April 1683October 1692-January 1692/3 (8 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, May 1693-March1694/5 (12 pieces)
  - Number 4: Jamaica, April 1695-24 August 1695 (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: Jamaica, 29 August 1695-5 August 1696 (11 pieces)
  - Number 6: Jamaica, August 1696-March1696/7 (10 pieces)
  - Number 7: Jamaica, May 1697-July 1700 (16 pieces)
- Volume XXII
  - Number 1: Jamaica, April 1678-May 1679 (8 pieces)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, June 1679-February1679/80 (11 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, 24 February1679/80-November 1682 (9 pieces)
  - Number 4: Jamaica, December 1679-March1681/2 (6 pieces)
  - Number 5: Jamaica, September 1684-August 1695 (6 pieces)
  - Number 6: Jamaica, July 1687-May 1690 (7 pieces)
  - Number 7: Jamaica, December 1683-February16 84/5 (9 pieces)
  - Number 8: Jamaica, March1684/5March1685/6 (9 pieces)
  - Number 9: Jamaica, 1681-2, 1685 (4 pieces)
  - Number 10: Jamaica, 1689-1691 (10 pieces)
- Volume XXIII
  - Number 1: Jamaica, 1661-1662January -March1681/2 (8 pieces) (Box Box 13)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, May -December 1682 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, September -November 1682 (8 pieces)
  - Number 4: Jamaica, November 1682-March1683 (8 pieces)
- Volume XXIV
  - Number 1: Jamaica, 13 March1683-June 1683 (9 pieces)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, July 1683-October 1683 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, 7 October 1683-14 December 1683 (9 pieces)
  - Number 4: Jamaica, 15 December 1683-3 March1683/4 (9 pieces)
  - Number 5: Jamaica, 9 March1683/4-12 June 1684 (12 pieces)
  - Number 6: Jamaica, June -November 1684-April 1689 (10 pieces)
- Volume XXV
  - Number 1: Jamaica, September 1684-December 1684 (9 pieces) (Box Box 14)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, February1684/5-2 November 1685 (10 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, 16 November 1685-1 May 1686 (12 pieces)
  - Number 4: Jamaica, 4 May 1686-September 1686 (13 pieces)
  - Number 5: Jamaica, October 1686-July 1687 (11 pieces)
  - Number 6: Jamaica, August 1687-April 1688 (14 pieces)
- Volume XXVI
  - Number 1: Jamaica, May 1681-20 August 1687 (11 pieces)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, 18 August 1687-10 May 1690 (10 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, April 1691-April 1692 (13 pieces)
- Volume XXVII
  - Number 1: Jamaica, May 1690-August 1692 (15 pieces) (Box Box 15)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, February1678/9-March1684/5 (12 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, November 1680-March1682/3 (14 pieces)
  - Number 4: Jamaica, July 1680-July 1689 (7 pieces)
  - Number 5: Jamaica, 1684-1684/5 (4 pieces)
- Volume XXVIII
  - Number 1: Jamaica, March1679/80-April 1687 (12 pieces)
  - Number 2: Jamaica, July 1681-March1688/9 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Jamaica, May 1690-May 1712 (9 pieces)
- Volume XXIX
  - Number 1: Barbados, November 1675-July 1678 (11 pieces) (Box Box 16)
  - Number 2: Barbados, November 1678-20 September 1677 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, 21 September 1679-August 1680 (11 pieces)
  - Number 4: (11 pieces) [this folder has been moved to oversize]
  - Number 5: Barbados, November 1706-June 1715 (16 pieces)
- Volume XXX
  - Number 1: Barbados, July 1678-April 1681 (10 pieces)
  - Number 2: Barbados, May 1681-August 1681 (6 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, September 1681-February1681/2 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Barbados, March1682-March[1682-3À] (9 pieces)
  - Number 5: Barbados, August 1682-April 1683 (13 pieces)
  - Number 6: Barbados, July 1683-April 1685 (13 pieces)
  - Number 7: Barbados, March1683/4-November 1695 (6 pieces)
- Volume XXXI
  - Number 1: Barbados, December 1682-November 1698 (10 pieces) (Box Box 17)
  - Number 2: Barbados, June 1689/90-March1691/2 (12 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, April 1692-November 1694 (11 pieces)
  - Number 4: Barbados, September 1685-March1695 (10 pieces)
  - Number 5: Barbados, March1688/9-July 1696 (9 pieces)
- Volume XXXII
  - Number 1: Barbados, May 1679-March1693 (9 pieces)
  - Number 2: Barbados, August 1681-November 1684 (9 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, October 1686-August 1687 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Barbados, September 1687-September 1688 (10 pieces)
  - Number 5: Barbados, October 1688-March1692/3 (13 pieces)
- Volume XXXIII
  - Number 1: Barbados, August 1683-April 1684 (7 pieces) (Box Box 18)
  - Number 2: Barbados, May 1684-October 1684 (5 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, December 1684-May 2, 1685 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Barbados, May 7, 1685-August 1, 1685 (11 pieces)
  - Number 5: Barbados, August 19, 1685-February1686/7 (12 pieces)
- Volume XXXIV
  - Number 1: Barbados, April 1680-September 3, 1681 (9 pieces)
  - Number 2: Barbados, September 25, 1682-October 1682 (6 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, November 1682-July 1683 (9 pieces)
  - Number 4: Barbados, July 1685-August 1694 (10 pieces)
  - Number 5: Barbados, April 1696-March1697/8 (11 pieces)
  - Number 6: Barbados, Jamaica, December 1695-March1713 (11 pieces)
- Volume XXXV
  - Number 1: Barbados, December 1679-January 1681 (11 pieces) (Box Box 19)
  - Number 2: Barbados, 1655-6, March1680/1-May 1683 (14 pieces)
  - Number 3: Barbados, March1683-October 31, 1683 (10 pieces)
  - Number 4: Barbados, October 31, 1683-November 1684 (15 pieces)
- Volume XXXVI
  - Number 1: Bermuda, February1684/5-December 1687 (14 pieces)
  - Number 2: Bermuda, November 1687-October 1688 (10 pieces)
  - Number 3: Bermuda, November 1688-June 1693 (14 pieces)
  - Number 4: Bermuda, November 1693-June 1697 (8 pieces)
  - Number 5: April 1698-January 1701/2 (9 pieces)